so this is from the shorter note on
gamma the word Dumber in his most
general sense is equivalent to thing ie
whatever is distinct from anything else
more precisely is what the thing is in
itself as opposed to how it is in the
footnote to that reads how a thing is is
a matter of structure that it's a say of
intentions chaykina or determinations
some Cara these are essentially negative
whereas gamma is positive
so in term in terms of that then he's
distinguishing what a thing is versus so
to see how a thing is but it may not be
obvious that those are two things that
can be distinguished in the first place
so to speak I was wondering if you had
anything comment or add about how you
would discern a thing for miss
determinations so to speak well okay so
that's where Jana saw manasu Cara comes
in basically knowing how to attend a
thing without making it another thing we
are making in a different thing so in
this in this particular passage you read
Dhamma is anything there has a nature to
manifest itself so feeling a thought or
perception memory it doesn't matter if
it's a reason experience as such it's a
thing it's a Dhamma so
you will discern then what that thing is
determined by by simultaneously being
able to discern what's present there
within that thing that it isn't that
thing now the problem is this requires
quite a refined as in proper way of
attending to to the to the well to the
fundamental core of the arisen thing
that's why John is someone a cigarillo
Nestle it room is wound means going
going back to the womb attending to the
womb of the arisen thing that is
simultaneously their present attending
to its base
that's what proper attention means in
the suitors the problem that people have
is if that proper tension is not
developed and trained and discerned what
you're going to do is when there is a
say a thing a has a reason instead of
seeing through it into not a still
within a but not that a people when they
look they overlook so then they see B
and B is just another thing then when
they look for the Sankara for the
determination of the experience B well
they see C which means they're not
seeing these things simultaneously
present they're following them in time
they're following them linearly or
logically and that's why that that's why
they can't understand the true nature of
Sankara because if they if a person
would understand that that's that's the
beginning of petite song father so the
present experience of such-and-such
nature without abandoning that
experience without over intending it
without under intending it you want to
discern peripherally in regard to the
present experience what else is there
that's what I meant in the previous
video about comma when I said the
intentionality behind your actions the
degree of those intentions it's given
beforehand as options and that's not
your doing nor it is your responsibility
not being able to see it on that level
you will automatically appropriate it
overly intended which means make it mine
which means result in acting out of it
so if you want to discern the
determination of the present there is an
experience of Dharma you need to see
within that present experience of Dhamma
that's why every petition father starts
with this this is the two simultaneous
to present things because yes when you
look at sin Cara's individually not in
the context of determining Dhamma there
are also things which means they're also
damaged as the Buddha described that
when he was describing the five
aggregates but you don't want to look
for the content of Sankara or the
content of damage you want to see the
relationship between Dhamma and that
which determines it which is not Dharma
that particular done so you want to see
relationship between a and that which is
simultaneously present that it's not
that a but not B either so by not giving
into a but not making it into B by not
confusing the two you get to understand
how a is presently determined presently
reason with presently reason causes as
well and that's why when they when they
ask the Buddhist he says how did you
cross he said you can't you can't cross
the shore by fighting the waves by
pulling backwards by standing still so
how did you cross through the shores but
not fighting the waves by not pulling
backwards by not standing still he has
crossed the stream the river but the
problem people have is because this is a
form of fighting the way over intending
oh there is there isn't a man a I look
for its cause as in I'm looking for B to
determine a and that's what most people
misunderstood but it's all bother they
think it's an explanation of the life of
the three life stages and so on they
think it's it's it's laid out in time
from ABCD efg and so on but it isn't
it's it's always always starts with the
present there isn't principle of with
this this is that's it and then the
Buddha will elaborate differently within
the same principle
depending on who you was teaching but
sometimes but it's on bottoms described
in 12 factors sometimes in eight
sometimes in sixteen it doesn't matter
what matters is the simultaneous
principle the principle of simultaneous
dependence and if you want to see what a
depends upon you can't look for B you
have to look within a which it is a name
without letting Dahmer's endure and then
no trying to over not trying to explain
to them as not trying to explain there
is a thing but allowing it to arise and
allow it resistant endure and while it
persists and indoors you get to see what
else is there within it that determines
and that's not that dumb
it's some kind of they're done but if
you look at B well then you need to look
now to find its own Sankara within that
be not like start drawing connections
between a and B and then provide an
explanation to yourself what the
determination is
this is going all into the next
paragraph now it starts sub-basin power
anita sebacean para dukkha sunday them
nuts up all determinations are permanent
all determinations are unpleasurable all
things are not self at self is
fundamentally a notion of mastery over
things but this notion is entertained :
if it is pleasurable it is only
pleasurable provided the mastery soon to
be permanent from mastery there's
essentially a kind of absolute
timelessness and moved moving of things
as undermined by impermanence is no
master at all but a mockery thus
regarding of a thing aid Emma as uptil
or self who survived only as so long as
a notion gives pleasure and it only
gives pleasure for us so long as that
Dhamma can be consider is permanent for
regarding a thing itself endowed with
the illusion of the kind of super
stability in time in itself as a demo
regarded as at that it some permanence
is not manifest for it as pleasant to
consider it as permanent but when it is
seen to be dependent upon other Dhamma
not consider to be burden if
impermanence does then become manifest
to see impermanence in what is regarded
as at that one must emerge from the
confines of the individual Demma itself
and see that it depends on what is
impermanent thus sub-basin Cara not
Donna Anita is said meaning all things that
Anita is said meaning all things that
things namah depend on are impermanent a
given Dhamma as a dumb regarded
is not accounted being so regarded
consider to be pleasant the one it is
seen to be dependent upon some other
dumb of that not being very his
Manifesta unpleasurable owing to the
invariable false perception of
permanence of super stability and one
not free from the conceit I am then its
own pleasure illness becomes manifest
thus sub-basin para not Dhamma sukha is
said when this is seen I went perception
of permanence and pleasure is under to
be false the notion this Dhamma is Maya
comes to an end in this replace with sub
made them enough
so so before you ask the question just
to do ad for that to that is that's
that's a commonly kind of miss miss read
with people say oh yeah the Buddha said
all things are impermanent all things
are suffering all things are not self
that's what I mean when you kind of
horville intend and expand and basically
use Dhamma that ends up being an
explanation just provides an explanation
that everything is impermanent and
everything is not yours and everything
is not yourself but if you read if you
look at the pali doesn't say that it
says all the terminations are
impermanent all determinations are
softly all things are not self so
there's that what I was discussing just
a few seconds ago that difference in the
simultaneously present things on a
different level as in the present Dhamma
present self is determined by present
things that have within it it cannot be
the self at the same time so gone in in
more in simpler terms if a person can
make a contemplation out of it again up
to Jinnah things things are mine because
I am but it's other way around it's
because you keep take take you keep
taking things to be for me
you keep assuming that you are so
appropriation of as mine comes first
structurally not temporarily which means
you can't have sense itself without a
sense of ownership being present there
simultaneously with that sense of self
and that's why for somebody who's
understood the Dhamma so Japan or higher
they have abandoned that automata but
they still have a degree of conceit that
would correspond to degree of
appropriation that they still maintain
in regard to things but ultimately of
course they're heading towards complete
freedom from it so in practical terms if
if a person wants to contemplate just
take your body for example don't don't
take some random objects because you
might well it's it's a sort of thing to
understand so you want to try as
accurately as possible you want to start
exactly as possible and the most
accurate the most factual thing that you
have is your body and that is something
your senses that is something that
everybody automatically appropriate sin
regards is mine and things that I am
like I can see hear taste touch because
I n it's actually other way around it's
because you keep seeing kami tasting
touching and so on you think you are as
in you think you are the owner of that
so if a person wants to wants to
undermine that sense you can't just give
such like explaining to yourself that
this body is impermanent and use like
medical jargon and so on because it
which assumes this external point of
view no you need to feel that
impermanence right through the heart of
that ownership and how you do it you do
it by allowing that ownership to arise
this body right here that's present
right now sitting on the chair talking
to you answering your questions can I
have this present body here answering
questioning on the chair in this forest
can I do that without the simultaneous
muscle inside of my chest the heart
beating and pumping blood without
without oxygen being pumped around my
body would I be able to operate without
my lungs being able to breathe air would
it be able to operate I wouldn't which
means any sense of ownership master
intentionality that I might exhibit is
directly determined simultaneously
determined or rather than determined by
the simultaneous presence of these other
functioning things that I cannot control
because it's you can't even conceive how
it would be to tell you how to stop and
it would be just completely involuntary
it's a non involve involuntary muscle
which means it just works on its own yet
your whole life depends upon it
now many people might think that
contemplate the heart and impermanence
of it but you don't want to contemplate
it as I said before after or before left
you want to contemplate it right through
the present thing of this appropriation
of this body in another video I was
talking about that like the simile the
simile of the chariot hobby besides made
out of path that is not real now you
want to see the path through the
existing phenomenon of the whole so the
contemplation of body parts will work
only as in it will result in this
passion and freedom from suffering and
this this owning of your own body and
your own sense of self which means it
will result in an utter contemplation of
parts will result in that if you see it
within the presently reasoned basis of
this appropriated body so this body that
I am this sentence is not talk in this
situation that I am in control of can be
undermined at any second by the beating
heart if it stops to be to pump that's
it I cannot I cannot continue existing
if these parts that comprise this entire
body if this part is they stopped
function if their dismembered if they
fail none of which you can control so
none of which you can control so
recognition of that of those
determinations of those parts
recognition of that it's they are
basically impermanent why because you
know they might be working now but they
cannot possibly work like this in this
particular arrangement forever it's just
inconceivable so that's the first recognition of the
so that's the first recognition of the
impermanence which then in itself while
this this cannot be pleasurable because
pleasant notion is the notion of
eternity it's going to be unchanged
forever stable and if you experience the
heart of your own issue as simple as a
impermanent and unpleasurable you disown
it automatically that's also another
thing I want to say so a person who
starts discerning service Ankara and
each service Ankara dukkha they don't
need to dangle in our case of Sabah
Dharma and artha know their experience
will automatically become dhamma anata
sabudana not
it will be automatically experiences not
mine itself
this sensor self this body this
situation by being actually
fundamentally rooted in that which is
completely other side of my reader
control undermines the ownership of this
very situation thus situation remains
unchanged in a way but then everything
changed changes because the ownership of
it has been removed
that's why arahant cannot be necessarily
recognized externally he still act
Stokes and does stuff normally like
everybody else does but there is no
ownership of any part of that thus there
is no any conceit of sense of self so
the girls the example you gave of seeing
your bodily situation that you find
yourself in determined by the presence
of let's say the heart what is the way
to bring your mind to this without
making the presence of your heart of
being as we say exactly without over at
attending it and then making a presence
of your heart another thing that now
you're not saying that the time in a
relationship of determination anymore
well the thing is you again we must not
you must not become a mindful of how you
feel in this present situation so the
present situation being felt right here
right now to this extent pleasant
unpleasant neutral and then just start
not allowing your mind to approach the
notion of a pumping heart often as a
determination not allow your mind to
approach it as a as an afterthought or
as before or is maybe as an explanation
but actually go through that situation
that's being felt and for most people
it's going to result in anxiety and
concern which is the inevitable
beginning that's why that's all in the sutras you
that's why that's all in the sutras you
read when people came to the Buddha and
they asked him buddy what is he teaching
you would explain the not-self when they
wouldn't fall on the ground beaten their
breasts and pulling their hair in
despair that's because they generally
understood what he was teaching but
obviously they did not let go of the
notion of self and stay experience
terror and they started they would shout
oh this will kill us this will destroy
us
this will obliterate us because they did
actually understand what he was
referring to so didn't misunderstood
something you wouldn't be that afraid
that's why sila needs to come first
mindfulness and restraint seeing the
danger in the slightest fault because
that will keep you together from falling
onto the ground and beating abreast and
and becoming desperate so that that's in
a matter that only so much a part of
finding determining that way
demeaning the presently similarly the
present determination within the present
there isn't thing so while the thing is
present you determine a determination
within it not before or after
so while this body here which is
automatically taking his mind without
all the thinking without making a
separate experience of a thought of my
pumping heart but stay with the thought
of this present experience peripherally
I discerned dependence that this
experience has upon a random beating
muscle of a heart heart muscle that's it
and then you'll feel it you'll start
feeling and when you start feeling it
you know you're doing it right you